Guide to the Keith Merrill Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Keith Merrill papers
1915-1985
1940-1945
MS 1480
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
The papers consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, cables, and printed material concerning economic warfare assembled by Keith Merrill when he served with the Board of Economic Warfare during World War II. Merrill intended to write a history of economic warfare, with emphasis on the violation of neutrality by the Swedes, and drafts of his manuscript are included in the papers.
Merrill, Keith, 1887-1959
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Rosemary Merrill Loring, 1988.
Biographical / Historical
Keith Merrill was born on April 2, 1887 in Minneapolis, Minnesota. He graduated from Yale University in 1911 and in 1914 he received a LL.B. from Harvard University. Merrill served in the United States Foreign Service from 1917 until 1937. He was in the U.S. Naval Reserve and served as assistant to Captain W. D. Puleston, Navy liaison officer to the Board of Economic Warfare, from 1942 to 1946. He married Mary Katherine Ayer on May 7, 1917; they had three children: Keith, Jr., Rosemary Katherine, and Eugenia Ayer.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, cables, and printed material concerning economic warfare assembled by Keith Merrill when he served with the Board of Economic Warfare during World War II. Merrill intended to write a history of economic warfare, with emphasis on the violation of neutrality by the Swedes, and drafts of his manuscript are included in the papers.
Arrangement
Arranged by record type.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Sweden -- Foreign relations; Merrill, Keith, 1887-1959; United States. Board of Economic Warfare
- Inventory
  - American Bosch case, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ball bearing production, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biography [summary of Merrill's activities in World War II], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence [alphabetical], 1937, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Economic warfare, 1919, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5 - 6)
  - German imports from neutrals, 1915-1918, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - IT&T Corporation subsidiaries, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - International law cases, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Naval period, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Negotiations
    - Argentina, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Portugal, 1943, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Spain [violations of neutrality], 1943-1945, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Sweden, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 14 - 19)
    - Switzerland, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Neutrals [general], 1943-1944, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Neutrality, personal [speech given by Merrill defending his neutral stance in the late 1930s], 1940 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Postwar period
    - Economic situation [memos pertaining to], 1945 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - German interests in United States, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "Government Organization for Waging Total War" [report], 1945 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Marshall Plan, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Neutrality, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Ruhr Plan, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Triumph of Unarmed Forces [book by Merrill]
    - Draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 29 - 30)
    - Notes and memos, 1945, 1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Unneutral neutrals, 1942-1947 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous [memos, notes, financial statements], 1917-1945, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)